<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><document><body>. 
SRI LANKA INSTITUTE OF INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY. 
M.Sc. in Information Technology. 
RESEARCH PROPOSAL. 
Productive Enhancement of  . 
 Software Quality And Standards.. 
Supervisor . 
Mr. Yashas Mallawaarchchi. 
Sri Lanka Institute of Information Technology . 
January 12, 2012. 
 Suminda S.Vinodahewa . 
PGM/IT/11/0408. 
“Computerized System” this is the most latest trend in the medium and small scale   business sector .In the large business organization they done achievement beginning of last decade, now enjoy the best advantages.. 
In today’s intensely competitive marketplace, companies have an insatiable need for information. Key to maintaining a competitive advantage is, understand what your customers want, what they need and the manner in which they want to receive your products or services. It is becoming increasingly clear that companies poised to experience the greatest success will be those firms that can effectively leverage their data to meet organizational needs, build solid relationships with their stakeholders and above all, meet the demands of today’s customers.. 
Considering the software houses, have a so many small and medium scale projects .However this project should have acceptable standards .It may be own standard or enforce standard by independent body, like ISO or CMMI .Ensue the trusted and reliable product come as the final. . 
Selecting the company by using the selecting parameters to identify process related activates and several sub processes. However, before the base line of this process or standards , there are number of factors and parties to be considering. Because, the several software houses to be practise several existing systems, which are already implemented and working their own standards.. 
However, this research will be an explorative study as an initial step, which might lead towards the next stage of identify uniqueness of each company process , based on the each processes , practises , and finally with the analysis of the data collected in this research.. 
After analysing of collected data get the better understanding over view of current statues of the software quality standards in the selected sample.  . 
Depending on the results obtained the discussion and conclusions will be drawn to inspect the element of define  this software quality standards for software customers as well as software employees .. 
The global economy of today demands that organizations adhere to the constantly changing needs of the customer. Additionally, the speed and dynamic nature of business often negates the time required for long-term planning and time-consuming implementations in order to stay ahead. Because of this, organizations must implement solutions that can be deployed quickly and in a cost-effective manner. So, how does an organization meet these ever-changing, complex requirements...that’s the reason should have a trusted and reliable business solution. . 
Computers are being used in an increasingly wide variety of application areas, and their intended and correct operation is often critical for business success and/or human safety. Developing or selecting high quality software products is therefore of prime importance. Comprehensive specification and evaluation of software product quality is a key factor in ensuring adequate quality. This can be achieved by defining appropriate quality characteristics, while taking account of the intended use of the software product. It is important that every relevant software product quality characteristic is specified and evaluated, whenever possible using validated or widely accepted measures.. 
 software quality is nothing but the besides being bug-free (the result of thorough software testing), will also be delivered on time, will meet the expectations of all parties involved including end-users, will have been delivered within the stated budget, and will be easy to maintain and upgrade over time. . 
Since the definition of quality though, may be subjective depending on who is defining it, software quality assurance may take in feedback from multiple areas of the enterprise, including end-users, supervisors and managers, the IT department responsible for maintaining the software, or in the case of commercial software being delivered to the public, feedback from the media, and other resellers, and customers.. 
A Software Quality Assurance Engineer is involved in the entire software development process to ensure the quality of the final product. This can include processes such as requirements gathering and documentation, source code control, code review, change management, configuration management, release management and the actual testing of the software. Software QA is often confused with Software Testing, but should not be. Testing is a big part of Software Quality Assurance, but it is not, by any means, the only part of it.. 
Developing or selecting high quality software products is therefore of prime importance. Comprehensive specification and evaluation of software product quality is a key factor in ensuring adequate quality. This can be achieved by defining appropriate quality characteristics, while taking account of the intended use of the software product. It is important that every relevant software product quality characteristic is specified and evaluated, whenever possible using validated or widely accepted measures. As quality characteristics and associated measures can be useful not only for evaluating a software product but also for defining quality requirements, related multipart International Standards  like ISO and CMMI. . 
The ISO 9000 family of standards relates to quality management systems and is designed to help organizations ensure they meet the needs of customers and other stakeholders. The standards are published by ISO, the International Organization for Standardization, and available through National standards bodies. ISO 9000 deals with the fundamentals of quality management systems, including the eight management principles  on which the family of standards. ISO 9001 deals with the requirements that organizations wishing to meet the standard have to fulfil. Third party certification bodies provide independent confirmation that organizations meet the requirements of ISO 9001. Over a million organizations worldwide  are independently certified, making ISO 9001 one of the most widely used management tools in the world today. Despite widespread use, however, the ISO certification process has been criticized as being wasteful and not being useful for all organizations.. 
In some large scale privet origination, like     and  have a certification of ISO, But ISO standards not only for  software but also a common for any industry . . 
Capability Maturity Model Integration (CMMI) is a process improvement approach whose goal is to help organizations improve their performance. CMMI can be used to guide process improvement across a project, a division, or an entire organization. Currently supported is CMMI Version 1.3.. 
CMMI in software engineering and organizational development is a process improvement approach that provides organizations with the essential elements for effective process improvement. CMMI is registered in the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office by Carnegie Mellon University.. 
According to the Software Engineering Institute (SEI, 2008), CMMI helps "integrate traditionally separate organizational functions, set process improvement goals and priorities, provide guidance for quality processes, and provide a point of reference for appraising current processes.". 
Apart from that standards considering the software companies have their own standard ,It also conceded. After analyzing all the standards and practices can propose the more practicable and productive method most suitable for our working patterns.  . 
  . 
Problem definition. 
Computers are being used in an increasingly wide variety of application areas, and their intended and correct operation is often critical for business success and/or human safety. Developing or selecting high quality software products is therefore of prime importance.. 
According to the studies, the high-level problems that it is identified in this area are;. 
How to ensure bugs free version can release to the client. Operation is often critical for business that should be more reliable , Most of the time live system come up with the bugs.. 
Design documents should be based line and updated . 
Software company should be process oriented not be the personal or team oriented.. 
How to handled the change request and client Business process changers.. 
In case of bugs in live system minimum time taken to recover it and how about the down time.. 
Base line of SRS and requirement comes under development period form the client. . 
UAT signoff process. . 
Considering the software company there have to consider the internal process , problems that it is identified in this area are:. 
Project schedule related issues and schedule variances.. 
Resource allocation . 
Documentation process issues and CR incorporated to the documents.. 
Software source maintainers and labeling.(VSS) . 
How to incorporate the Onsite changers to company sources.. 
Enforce the QA metrics.. 
RTM map and CR incorporating  process.. 
Every time conclude a study or task force on the software development process, recommendation that comes out loud and clear “Need to adapt the best practises in the industry “. 
Couldn’t find quality assurance and stranded evaluation tool to fine the best software companies for Business Automations.. 
Implement the quality assurances tools which coved software quality stranded. Introduce the user friendly Tool to non technical customer to selecting the best software company for Business Automations. 
Customer should get competitive advantages through Business Automation, which means that they will select the best company as well as in and out understanding of Business continuity (Live systems without issues or downtimes).   . 
Get the opportunity to analysis on most recent data, as well as the historical data and this could be bring most advance tool to the customer that would gain competitive benefits to select the most suitable company.. 
Provide the “code of best practices” and “check list” for software as a tools for achieve the goal of Quality and bugs free product. . 
software workers can select the convenient please to works with more arrange environment. . 
Evaluate ability to maintainers, customer supports . . 
To fulfil the objectives of the research, One of the main research area as follows:. 
software company process related issues and project schedules .. 
Quality assurances process practice in the company.. 
Process related documentation. (RTM,SRS). 
Customer handling.. 
requirement base line.. 
CR handling.. 
Maintainers process of live systems. . 
The approach for gathering required information for the research would be to refer scholar articles, journals and previous research publications in the subject matter fields. Involved with several parties and each party will be having a different experiences .As well as gathering the own process details form selected leading  IT companies. Some of the forms related to that filed discus the practical issues there faced ,It also will help to get clear picture of the problem. . 
The information gathered would be analyzed using statistical means and will elaborate using graphs and relevant tables to gain more insights. As a basic statistical tools, planning to use Microsoft Office Excel 2007. . 
Outcomes from the previous approaches would be used to design. To study of the existing process will help to billed most suitable tools to software company and the software client to Automate the business less amount of unpleasant experiences.     . 
Data collection is the one of the most important part of the research. Can be planed it as a high level or over view of data collection is done as a initial step. Data would be collecting from groups. Necessary to gather data from each and every involving parties.. 
After completing high level data gathering , then only go for the in detail data collection .All the company which selected have to collect their data separately. . 
Have to get all the process related data and after that get the data from active involves. Should collect the process draw back and practical issues it’s very important to get clear understand. . 
In the initial stage of high level data gathering it will be an open ended interviews but in the detail level it will be a funnelling questions, mean that handing the question to fulfils over objectives.. 
 . 
Every time we conclude a study or task force on the subject of software development process recommendation that comes out loud and clear.” Need to adopt the best practise in the industry”. Research has to begin with collecting data and  information  from selected companies and analyse finally get the conclusions. Most of the company have their own methods it’s important to improve of the process that practice now and also it would be as an experiment of new achievements.. 
Gathering data is time consuming and tactic would be more essay to collect data as a fulfil of requirements. Estimated project schedule summery given bellow.  . 
   . 
Initialize the research &amp; Scope . 
Supervisor discussion 2 weeks . 
literature review3weeks . 
Prepare proposal 2 weeks . 
Review by Supervisor 1 week. 
High level data gathering and selecting peoples . 
To get information3 weeks . 
Get the own process information 2 weeks. 
Analysis the data  3weeks . 
Supervisor Discussion and comments  1 day . 
Implementing the tool with check list5weeks. 
Final supervisor review 1 week. 
Complete the final projects 4weeks  . 
The following facilities would be needed to carry out the research successfully.. 
At least two computers with 3 GHz core 2 processor speed, 3GB RAM and 500GB hard disk. 
Microsoft Excel 2007 and office package.   . 
3.5 Mbps Broadband Internet Connectivity.. 
ISO 9001 is the internationally recognised standard for the quality management of businesses.“Quality Standards from Approachable Auditors “ISO 9001 - Quality Management Standard ; ” http://www.isoqar.com/iso9001/qualintro.htm”. 
CMMI (Capability Maturity Model Integration) is a process improvement approach that provides organizations. “Software  Engineering Institute” . http://www.sei.cmu.edu/cmmi/. 
Sri Lanka Software Testing Board (SLSTB) is a non-profit organization that represents the national industry interests and promotes the broad profession of software testing.” http://www.sl-stb.org/about_slstb.html”. 
“Software Quality and Standards” PDF presentation Dr. James A. Bednar &amp; Dr. David Robertson; http://www.inf.ed.ac.uk/teaching/courses/seoc2/2004_2005/slides/quality.pdf. 
"Software Quality Engineering" To help organizations worldwide significantly improve their software practices all along the development lifecycle. http://www.sqe.com/. 
GoldenGate Software, I. (2009, February). “Real-Time Data Integration for Data Warehousing and Operational BI”. San Francisco, USA: GoldenGate Software, Inc.You +1'd this publicly. Undo. 
www.swquality.com/Cached . 
29 Mar 2011 – The Software Quality Page Your connection to the world of software quality, standards and process improvement.. 
File Format: Microsoft Powerpoint - Quick View Software quality management. Concerned with ensuring that the required level of quality is achieved in a software product. Involves defining appropriate quality ... www.comp.lancs.ac.uk/computing/resources/IanS/SE7/.../ch27.ppt. 
www.hq.nasa.gov/office/codeq/doctree/87398.pdf. 
File Format: PDF/Adobe Acrobat - Quick View disciplines of software quality, software reliability, software safety, software verification and validation, and independent verification and validation. This standard .... 
www.hq.nasa.gov/office/codeq/doctree/87398.pdf. 
You +1'd this publicly. Undo File Format: PDF/Adobe Acrobat - Quick View. 
disciplines of software quality, software reliability, software safety, software verification and validation, and independent verification and validation. This standard,. 
www.mastercontrol.com/quality-management-software/Cached - Similar. 
You +1'd this publicly. A Quality Management Software System Helps in Automating Paper-Based Quality Management Processes to comply with regulations.. 
ETL: Extract, Transform, Load. 
SRS: Software requirement specification.. 
CR: Change Request. 
RTM: Requirements Trisibility Matrix.. 
VSS: Visual sources safe  . 
OLAP: Online Analytical Processing. 
QA: Quality Assurance. 
UAT: User Acceptance Test  . 
  </body><titles><title scale="5">Abstract</title><title scale="5">Background of software quality standards </title><title scale="5">Research objectives and Research questions</title><title scale="5">Methodology</title><title scale="5">Data collection</title><title scale="5">Working plan and time schedule</title><title scale="5">Feasibility</title><title scale="5">References</title><title scale="5">Acronyms</title><title scale="4">Schedule </title><title scale="3">Considering Quality Characteristics</title><title scale="3">Software Quality Assurance</title><title scale="3">Software Quality Standards </title><title scale="3">ISO 9000</title><title scale="3">CMMI</title><title scale="3">Research questions</title><title scale="3">Research Objective </title><title scale="3">Benefits  </title><title scale="3">Research Area</title><title scale="3">Information Gathering Approach</title><title scale="3">Analytical Approach</title><title scale="3">Designing  and Conclusion Approach</title><title scale="2">Feasibility requirements</title><title scale="1">RESEARCH PROPOSAL</title><title scale="1"> Suminda S.Vinodahewa </title><title scale="1">PGM/IT/11/0408</title><title scale="1">Problem definition</title></titles></document>